const e="We could not find what you asked for, but got you this",t="englishlit",o=200,i=120,a=[{id:156,question:"Mazisi Kunene is an African poet from  ",option:{a:"Ghana ",b:"Nigeria  ",c:"Malawi  ",d:"South Africa"},section:"Question is based on African and Non-African Poetry  ",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2013"},{id:39,question:"The name of the place where Tess and Angel Clare meet each other the second time is: ",option:{a:"Tratridge ",b:"Brazil ",c:"Dubeyfield",d:"Talbothays farm."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2007"},{id:267,question:"‘l will be brief, for my short date of breath Is not so long as is a tedious tale.’ The statement above is in reference to the speaker’s",option:{a:"retirement",b:"imminent death",c:"state of health",d:"short-tempered nature."},section:"Based on William Shakespeare’s Romeo and Juliet.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:209,question:"The speaker is",option:{a:"Gonzalo",b:"Antonio",c:"Sebastian",d:"Alonso"},section:"WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE: The Tempest<br><br> 		You cram these words into mine ears against<br> 		The stomach of my sense. Would l had never<br> 		Married my daughter there! For, coming thence,<br> 		My son is lost, and, in my rate, she too,<br> 				(Act II, Scene One, lines 99 - 102)<br>",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:423,question:"One of the themes found in vanity is",option:{a:"Destruction",b:"Innocence",c:"Dilemma",d:"Clash of cultures"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2017"},{id:93,question:"Romeo’s death becomes inevitable because ",option:{a:"Emire Lawrence’s is not delivered: ",b:"Juliet is married to Paris ",c:"Romeo kills Tybalt in a duel ",d:"Juliet has committed suicide."},section:"Question is based on William Shakespeare’s Romeo and Juliet",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:63,question:"Identify the odd one out of these types of imagery  ",option:{a:"visual imagery  ",b:"tactile imagery  ",c:"synesthesia  ",d:"literal imagery."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:433,question:"The figure of speech in which a poet implicity compares an object or idea with another totally different object or idea is called a ",option:{a:"Smile",b:"Denotation",c:"Connotation",d:"Metaphor"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2017"},{id:129,question:"Comic relief is used in a work of art to  ",option:{a:"to suspend disbelief  ",b:"to maneuver the portal of narration  ",c:"to create chiaroscuro  ",d:"to suspend to tension "},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2012"},{id:347,question:"An expression that signifies a whole through its significant parts is",option:{a:"synesthesia",b:"synecdoche",c:"metonymy",d:"allegory"},section:"based on General Literary Principles.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:74,question:"Literary device that creates a mental picture of   a situation is ",option:{a:"imagery ",b:"symbolism ",c:"flashback ",d:"epilogue"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:248,question:"Pun as a literary device deals with",option:{a:"placing two opposite phrase",b:"placing words side by side",c:"playing on words",d:"arrangement of words"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:217,question:"‘Ariel and all his quality’ mean Ariel and",option:{a:"all at his command",b:"the quality of a spirit",c:"his band of spirits",d:"an ability to cause mischief"},section:"WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE: The Tempest<br><br>  		Ariel:	All hail, great master! Grave sir, hail! I come<br> 			To answer thy best pleasure; be’t to fly, <br> 			To swim, to dive into the fire, to ride<br> 			On the curled clouds, to thy strong bidding task<br> 			Ariel and all his quality. <br> 			(Act I, Scene  Two, lines 189 - 193)	",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:28,question:'"As virtuous men pass wildly away, and higher to their souls, to go,  Whilst some of their sad friends to say,  "The breadth goes now", and some say "No".  The tone of this poem is generally ',option:{a:"appreciative ",b:"serious",c:"imaginative ",d:"conversational."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2007"},{id:42,question:`"Naett" in Leopold Sedar Senmghor's "I will Pronounce you Name" refers to: `,option:{a:"South Africa ",b:"a women ",c:"a man ",d:"Black Africa."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2007"},{id:457,question:"He made the speech to ",option:{a:"Othello",b:"Lago",c:"Desdemona",d:"Cassion"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:133,question:"The general  idea in the extract is ",option:{a:"neglect  ",b:"praise  ",c:"ridicule  ",d:"worship"},section:`(Extract for question)
Agosu, if you go tell them,
Tell Nyidevu, Kpeti, and Kove
That they have done us evil;
Tell them house is falling 
And the tree in the fence
Have been eaten by termites 
`,image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2012"},{id:557,question:"The flat character in a literary work",option:{a:"Is the same as the round character",b:"Cannot be found in an allegory",c:"Is capable of growing",d:"Always embodies a quality"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:505,question:"The handkerchief the speaker mentioned belongs to",option:{a:"Othello",b:"Cassio",c:"Bianca",d:"Lago"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:121,question:"“The animals saw no reason to disbelieve him, especially as they could no longer remember very clearly  what conditions had been like before the rebellion. All the same, there were days when they felt that they would sooner have had less figures and more food”. The tone of the passage above is quite: ",option:{a:"exhilarating ",b:"cynical ",c:"optimistic ",d:"obsequious."},section:"Question is  based on literary appreciation",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:393,question:"In Birago Diop's Vanity, the poem addresses the need for Africans not to neglect their",option:{a:"Past or root",b:"Present and future",c:"Nature and principles ",d:"Culture and norms"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:126,question:"The exclusive right given to authors to protect their works from unlawful production or reproduction is   ",option:{a:"A copyright  ",b:"an authority to write  ",c:"an author’s right   ",d:"a constitutional provision "},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2012"},{id:189,question:"A character that develops in the course of  a novel or play is described as",option:{a:"flat",b:"antagonist",c:"round",d:"protagonist"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:147,question:"The national day in The Old Man and the Medal is  ",option:{a:"1st of October  ",b:"27th of May  ",c:"12th June  ",d:"14th July"},section:`Question is based on Ferdinand Oyono’s
The Old Man and medal and The joys of motherhood   
`,image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2012"},{id:388,question:"With a little coercion, a touch of blackmail, and a bit of deceit, poison is made to meet",option:{a:"Kabira and Sylv Po",b:"Mute and Kabria",c:"Fofo and Baby T",d:"Onko and Baby T"},section:"Question 27 is based on Amma Darko's Faceless",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:285,question:"In Kunene’s ‘A Heritage of Liberation,’ freedom is to be achieved through the efforts of",option:{a:"the old generation",b:"new generation",c:"present generation",d:"successive generations."},section:"Based on selected poems from Johnson, 	R. et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyirvka, W. (ed.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; Maduka, C.T. et al: Exam Focus: Literature in English; Eruvbetine, A. E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D. I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G.: Naked Soles.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:233,question:"In the novel, the society puts high value on",option:{a:"egalitarianism",b:"male ascendancy",c:"procreation",d:"gender equity"},section:"Based on Buchi Emecheta’s  	The Joys of  Motherhood.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:469,question:'In the poem "Birches" the narrator looks at the borch trees in the forest and imagines that their bent nature is as a result of a ____________ "swinging" on them',option:{a:"Monkey",b:"Child",c:"Boy",d:"Man"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:336,question:"The end of “Give Me The Minstrel’s Seat”, seems to suggest that one needs the",option:{a:"support of others",b:"complete command of one’s wives",c:"support of one’s kinsmen",d:"aid of poets"},section:"based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New poetry from Africa; Soyinka W. (ed.): Poems of Black Africa: Senanu, K E and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eels.): Exam Focus: Lit-erature in English; Eruvbetine, A. E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination guides; Nwoga, D.I (ed.): West African Verse andAdeoti G: Naked Soles.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:274,question:"Winston Smith begins his rebellion against the power of the state by",option:{a:"purchasing arms",b:"keeping a private diary",c:"opposing the law",d:"educating the youth."},section:"Based on George Orwell’s Nineteen  	Eighty-Four.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:87,question:"‘The madman has entered our house with violence  defiling our sacred grounds claiming the single truth of the universe bending down our priest with iron’. Mazzizi Kunnene’s progress the imagery of the line above captures the idea of ",option:{a:"coercion ",b:"truth ",c:"religiosity ",d:"persuasion."},section:`‘You kiss her on the cheek 
You kiss her open-sore lips
As white people do.
You suck slimy saliva
From each other’s moths.
As white people do.
Okot P’ Breck’s song of larie
`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:257,question:"From the poem above, shadow means",option:{a:"famine",b:"bleak future",c:"period of sufferings",d:"abstract ideas"},section:"And your laughter like a flame<br>	 	Piercing the shadows<br> 	Has revealed Africa to me beyond<br> 	The snow of yesterday<br>",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:319,question:`‘...So tedious is this day<br>
	As is the night before some festival<br>
	To an impatient child that hath new robes<br>
	And may not wear them.’<br>
The literary device used in the excerpt is`,option:{a:"euphemism",b:"simile",c:"sarcasm",d:"bathos"},section:"based on William Shake¬speare’s  	Romeo and Juliet.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:92,question:"The multiple deaths in the play serve as a punishment for ",option:{a:"impatience on the part of  Romeo and Juliet; ",b:"imposing life partners on children ",c:"disobedience of the protagonists  ",d:"Tybalt’s fiery temper."},section:"Question is based on William Shakespeare’s Romeo and Juliet",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:161,question:"The medal in the novel is a symbol of  ",option:{a:"ungodliness   ",b:"victory   ",c:"admiration ",d:"deceit "},section:"Question is  based on Ferdinand Oyono’s The Old Man and the Medal.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2013"},{id:415,question:"The mission of the white man is revealed and Soko is enlisted into the",option:{a:"Plan of work",b:"Game plan",c:"Mission act",d:"Music game"},section:`Question 14 and 15 are based on Dele Charley's "The Blood of a stranger"`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2017"},{id:181,question:"A metrical foot in which a stressed syllable is followed by an unstressed syllable is",option:{a:"iambic",b:"spondaic",c:"trochaic",d:"dactylic"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:428,question:`Robert frost's "Birches" portrays that life can be hard for`,option:{a:"Children",b:"Youth",c:"Adult",d:"Society"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2017"},{id:333,question:"‘Pregnant clouds Ride Safely on its back’ Pregnant clouds in Rubadiri’s “An AfricanThunderstorm implies”",option:{a:"uncertainty",b:"calmness",c:"disbelief",d:"fertility"},section:"based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New poetry from Africa; Soyinka W. (ed.): Poems of Black Africa: Senanu, K E and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eels.): Exam Focus: Lit-erature in English; Eruvbetine, A. E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination guides; Nwoga, D.I (ed.): West African Verse andAdeoti G: Naked Soles.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:259,question:"The poem can be described as",option:{a:"a lyric",b:"an epic",c:"a sonnet",d:"an elegy"},section:"Move him into the sun,<br> 	Gently its touch awoke him once, ,<br> 	At home, whispering of  fields unsown,<br> 	Always it woke him even in France,<br> 	Until this morning and this snow,<br> 	If anything might rouse him now ,<br> 	This kind old sun will know,<br> 	Think how it wakes the seeds,<br> 	Woke, once, the clays of a cold star,<br> 	Are limbs, so dear achieved, are,<br> 	sides Full nerved still warm too hard ,<br> 	to stir Was it, for this the clay grew,<br> 	tall? O what made fatuous sunbeams ,<br> 	toil To break earth’s sleep at all. ,<br>",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:123,question:"The poet personal in the poem above is: ",option:{a:"resigned to fate  ",b:"a holy man  ",c:"a daily traveler  ",d:"suffering but optimistic. "},section:`“I come and go
a pilgrim
grubbily unkempt
stubbornly cheerful
defiantly whistling hope
and grubbing for crumbs of success
out of all near-defeats.
`,image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:343,question:"The use of sound pattern to suggest meaning in poetry is",option:{a:"rhythm",b:"mimics",c:"lyric",d:"metonymy"},section:"based on General Literary Principles.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:13,question:"What figure of speech is “shining coal”?  ",option:{a:"paradox ",b:"irony  ",c:"oxymoron",d:"paronomasia"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2006"},{id:64,question:"When a poet uses mainly soft vowel sounds in a poem, the texture of the poem is ",option:{a:"mellifluous ",b:"harsh ",c:"assonantal ",d:"neutral "},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:113,question:"The tone in Gbemisola Adeoti’s Naked soles” is that of ",option:{a:"reconciliation  ",b:"lamentation  ",c:"exhortation ",d:"admiration"},section:"Question is are based on selected African poems.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:227,question:"Where does the play take place?",option:{a:"On the street",b:"In George’s place",c:"In Aunt’s house",d:"In Ofosu’s place"},section:"Based on J.C. De Graft’s  	Sons and Daughter. ",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:91,question:"The literary device  which anticipates that an event will take place is best described as ",option:{a:"parody ",b:"flashback ",c:"foreshadowing ",d:"rising action "},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:219,question:"X and Y are",option:{a:"Antonio and Alonso",b:"Sebastian and Alonso",c:"Antonio and Gonzalo",d:"Sebastian and Gonzalo"},section:"WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE: The Tempest<br><br> 		<strong>X:</strong> We two, my lord,<br> 			Will guard your person while you take your rest, <br> 			And watch your safety. <br> 			<br> 		<strong>Y:</strong> Thank you. - Wondrous heavy. <br> 			(Act II, Scene One, lines 184 - 187)",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:533,question:"One of the universal themes of the novel is",option:{a:"Vengeance",b:"Property and inheritance",c:"Religious hypocrisy",d:"Marriage"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:363,question:`In Hardcastle's house, Hrdcastle and several "awkward servants" enter, the former instructing them on how to appear`,option:{a:"Disgusting",b:"Sophisticated",c:"Friendly",d:"Fuming"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:251,question:"Satirical writing employs",option:{a:"epigram",b:"synecdoche",c:"irony",d:"onomatopoeia"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:216,question:"Before Ariel’s entry",option:{a:"Ferdinand has brought in some wood",b:"Prospero has put Miranda to sleep",c:"Caliban had been swearing at Prospero",d:"Trinculo had discovered Caliban’s cloak"},section:"WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE: The Tempest<br><br>  		Ariel:	All hail, great master! Grave sir, hail! I come<br> 			To answer thy best pleasure; be’t to fly, <br> 			To swim, to dive into the fire, to ride<br> 			On the curled clouds, to thy strong bidding task<br> 			Ariel and all his quality. <br> 			(Act I, Scene  Two, lines 189 - 193)	",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:183,question:"A ballad is essentially a ____________ poem",option:{a:"descriptive",b:"dramatic",c:"pastoral",d:"narrative"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:152,question:"Joe de Graft’s Sons and daughters is an example of ",option:{a:"domestic comedy ",b:"dark comedy ",c:"restoration comedy ",d:"comedy of error"},section:"Question is  based  on Joe de Graft’s Sons and Daughters.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2013"},{id:151,question:"James Ofosu is pleased with George because he studies ",option:{a:"Law  ",b:"Accountancy ",c:"Engineering   ",d:"Medicine "},section:"Question is  based  on Joe de Graft’s Sons and Daughters.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2013"},{id:465,question:"The above extract is an example of",option:{a:"Intimidation and frustration",b:"Conflict and clash of cultures",c:"Man engages the world as in a contest",d:"The twist in human fate"},section:'Ambush by Gbemisola Adeoti. "The fishers turn home at dusk" Sad without a good catch. Infants shudder home the grizzled ones snatch their gut"',image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:325,question:"The main concern of Winston in the novel is to",option:{a:"take power for himself",b:"acquire wealth",c:"overthrow the party",d:"bring social change"},section:"based on George Orwell’s  	Nineteen Eighty-Four",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:118,question:"But the pigs were so clever that they could think of a way around every difficulty. As for the horses, they know every inch of the field and in fact understood the business of mowing and raking”. The dominant literary device in the excerpt above is ",option:{a:"repetition ",b:"mimesis ",c:"ellipsis ",d:"personification."},section:"Question is  based on literary appreciation",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:173,question:"The figurative devices in the excerpt above are  ",option:{a:"rhyme and metaphor  ",b:"alliteration and assonance  ",c:"repetition and simile  ",d:"rhyme and onomatopoeia "},section:`“Her voice is a shell borne by the waves to crack the egg my soul sorely craves”
Segun Adekoya  “Love Blues” 
`,image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2013"},{id:527,question:"A play is dram because",option:{a:"It is written in verse",b:"It can be acted on stage",c:"It contains characters",d:"It does not contain any story"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:302,question:"‘You do not have to be brutal to be a soldier, or rather you are brutal not because you are a soldier, but because there is a sadist, a rapist, a fascist and a murderer in you who is waiting for war and army uniforms to give them expression.’ ( Festus lyayi: Heroes ) The speaker here contends that",option:{a:"soldiers are generally wicked",b:"human nature has to do with a profession",c:"soldiers are characteristically gentle",d:"the latent brutality in man finds expression in war."},section:"based on Literary Appreciation.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:139,question:"Aaron’s brother who trains as an accountant is  ",option:{a:"George  ",b:"Awere  ",c:"Owusu  ",d:"Kofi"},section:"Question is based on Joe de Graft’s Sons and daughters",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2012"},{id:459,question:'The statement "Our wars are done" implies that',option:{a:"They have won the battle",b:"The Turkish attack will not happen",c:"The Turkish fleet was broken apart",d:"Othello's ship got sunk"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:171,question:"The type of sonnet that has an octave and a sestet has its origin in  ",option:{a:"England  ",b:"Spain ",c:"Portugal   ",d:"Italy"},section:"Question is based on General literary principles.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2013"},{id:365,question:"One of the themes in She Stoops to Conquer is based on",option:{a:"Appearance and reality",b:"Destruction",c:"Abuse of power and position",d:"Frustration"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:31,question:"Face thrives on ",option:{a:"big events ",b:"promotion ",c:"absurdity ",d:"incidents."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2007"},{id:168,question:"In the Newspeak language, “duckspeak” is a word that simultaneously  refers to ",option:{a:"love and admiration  ",b:"knowledge and ignorance  ",c:"now and then ",d:"abuse and praise "},section:"Question is based on George Orwell’s Nineteen Eighty Four",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2013"},{id:382,question:"Yaremi in a dilemma, not knowing whether she is to shed tears of ",option:{a:"Gratitude or tears of sorrow",b:"Ingratitude or tears of Joy",c:"Gratitude or tears of joy",d:"Happiness"},section:"Question 21 is based on Bayo Adebowale's Lonely Days",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:276,question:"The events following the ceremony confirm Meka’s",option:{a:"disillusion with the whites",b:"satisfaction with the medal",c:"contribution to the colonialists",d:"admiration for the church."},section:"Based on Ferdinand Oyono’s The Old Man and the Medal.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:427,question:'In Alfred Tennyson "Crossing the Bar," the major themes are',option:{a:"Death and hope",b:"Beauty and quest",c:"Formal education and imprisonment",d:"Sinners and the Righteous"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2017"},{id:441,question:"In literay criticism, a casual refrence to a figure is ",option:{a:"Alliteration",b:"Allegory",c:"Ambiguity",d:"Allusion"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2017"},{id:27,question:`"That that is why we must acc-c-cept the universal d-d-dome, b-b-because there is no d-d-d-direction, The b-b-bridge is the d-d-dome of religion and b-b- bridges d-don't just g-g-go from here to the there; a bridge also face backwards". Wole Soyinka, The Interpreters. The idiolectical feature of the character's speech is the `,option:{a:"repetition of consonant sounds ",b:"repetition of initial consonant sounds ",c:"duplication of consonant sound clusters ",d:"multiplication of diphthongs."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2007"},{id:356,question:`	Oh, the market is set like the hub of a wheel <br>
	And it pulfs 	like a magnet strong <br>
	It is easy to tell <br>
	How it casts its spell <br>
	And draws all the crowds along. <br><br>
The sound device used in the extract above is`,option:{a:"rhyme",b:"alliteration",c:"emphasis",d:"assonance"},section:"based on Literary Appreciation",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:207,question:"The “advocate” and the “impostor” are",option:{a:"conspirators",b:"enemies",c:"suspicious of each other",d:"attracted to each other"},section:"	WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE: The Tempest<br><br> 		Silence! One word more<br> 		Shall make me chide thee, if not hate thee. What!<br> 		An advocate for an impostor! Hush!<br> 		(Act I, Scene Two, lines 478 - 480)",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:556,question:"The literary device which anticipates that an event will take place is best described as",option:{a:"Foreshadowing",b:"Rising action",c:"Flashback",d:"Parody"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:150,question:"Aaron’s painting is purchased by an American collector for the sum of ",option:{a:"250 dollars  ",b:"220 pounds ",c:"260 cedis  ",d:"280 francs "},section:"Question is  based  on Joe de Graft’s Sons and Daughters.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2013"},{id:470,question:'In "the pulley" the reason why God took the decision to withhold rest, the most important of all his gifts, from man is revealed in',option:{a:"Second stanza",b:"First stanza",c:"Third stanza",d:"Fourth stanza"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:452,question:"Yaremi's major source of income generates from",option:{a:"Oil business",b:"Taffeta clothes",c:"Farming",d:"Bridal bangles"},section:`Questions 11 to 12 are based on Bayo Adebowale's "Lonely Days"`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:553,question:'In "Raider of the Treasure Trove" by Lade Wosornu, "the gems of your dreams in line 2, the poet is describing the',option:{a:"The cost of anger in man's life",b:"Homily to eschew anger",c:"The value of life",d:"A man's purpose being the reason for his life"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:366,question:"When Jeremy, one of the servants enters drunkenly and makes a fool of himself, Marlow refuses to discipline him but instead mocks",option:{a:"Hardcastle's request",b:"Hastings' request",c:"Tony's request",d:"Kate's request"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:351,question:"A group of three lyric stanzas in classical Greek poetry is referred to as",option:{a:"triplet",b:"triolet",c:"trilogy.",d:"triad"},section:"based on General Literary Principles.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:222,question:"What has happened to all the other characters in the scene?",option:{a:"They have been made deaf and dumb",b:"Ariel has put them all to sleep",c:"They have been sent away",d:"Prospero has put them to sleep"},section:"WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE: The Tempest<br><br> 		<strong>X:</strong> We two, my lord,<br> 			Will guard your person while you take your rest, <br> 			And watch your safety. <br> 			<br> 		<strong>Y:</strong> Thank you. - Wondrous heavy. <br> 			(Act II, Scene One, lines 184 - 187)",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:159,question:'‘fellow wayfarer…what good news do you bring me?" The statement above is addressed by Meka to',option:{a:"the Commandant’s messenger ",b:"a passing dog   ",c:"a dove ",d:"Engamba "},section:"Question is  based on Ferdinand Oyono’s The Old Man and the Medal.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2013"},{id:315,question:"What causes the strained relationship between James and Lawyer B?",option:{a:"Betrayal of trust",b:"Standard of education",c:"Working experience",d:"Family differences"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:314,question:"The plot of the play is,",option:{a:"linear",b:"cyclical",c:"complicated",d:"episodic"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:116,question:"In Wendy Cope’s Sonnet VII,  poetry is regarded as a God –given weapon to: ",option:{a:"musicians ",b:"recluses ",c:"nomads ",d:"pilgrims."},section:"Questions is based on Non-African Poetry",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:215,question:"Prospero has actually",option:{a:"raised a storm at sea",b:"punished Miranda",c:"dismissed Fedinand",d:"commanded Ariel to disappear"},section:"WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE: The Tempest<br><br>  		Ariel:	All hail, great master! Grave sir, hail! I come<br> 			To answer thy best pleasure; be’t to fly, <br> 			To swim, to dive into the fire, to ride<br> 			On the curled clouds, to thy strong bidding task<br> 			Ariel and all his quality. <br> 			(Act I, Scene  Two, lines 189 - 193)	",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:321,question:"Shakespeare depicts love and idealism through the",option:{a:"party at tire Capulets’",b:"lovers’ tomb at the end",c:"brawl between Romeo and Tybalt",d:"balcony scene in the second Act."},section:"based on William Shake¬speare’s  	Romeo and Juliet.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:411,question:"The lady of the house Mrs. Thomas is woken up from her sleep by the clanging of an alarm clock, she shouts order at her sons",option:{a:"Buddy and Jack",b:"Dalton and Bigger",c:"Paeggy and Jack",d:"Bigger and Buddy"},section:`Question 10 and 11 are based on Richard Wright's "Native Son"`,image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2017"},{id:136,question:"“Your hand is heavy, Night, upon by brow” is an example of  ",option:{a:"hyperbole  ",b:"onomatopoeia  ",c:"apostrophe  ",d:"oxymoron "},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2012"},{id:104,question:"He already had five wives and was soon going to break the legs of the antelope for the sixth time’. The expression ‘break the legs of the antelope’ means to: ",option:{a:"be ON honeymoon ",b:"offer ritual sacrifice ",c:"hunt for antelopes  ",d:"have a  new baby."},section:"Question is  based on Oyono’s Old man hand the medal",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:249,question:"In a narrative poem, the poet attempts to",option:{a:"summarize a story",b:"describe a place",c:"preach a sermon",d:"tell a story"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:552,question:`Oumar Farouk Sesay's "The Song of the Women of my Land" portrays a society that is`,option:{a:"Tough with women in olden days African society",b:"Hunted by the evil land",c:"Gripped with fear",d:"Unstable"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:391,question:"I do beseech you. Though I perchance an vicious in my guess, As I confess, it tis my nature's plague. To spy into abuses, and of my jealousy. Shape faults that are not that your wisdom yet, from one that so imperfectly conceits. In the above excerpt, who is the speaker?",option:{a:"Othello",b:"Desdemona",c:"Lago",d:"Emilia"},section:"Question 30 is based on William Shakespeare's Othello.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:243,question:"Both comedy and tragedy have",option:{a:"happy ending",b:"climax",c:"tragic hero",d:"stanza"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:451,question:"Peggy leads Bigger into the kitchen and asks him to sit down while she gets the",option:{a:"Fruits ready",b:"Dinner ready",c:"Food ready",d:"Drinks ready"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:499,question:`Dele Charley's "The Blood of a Stranger". The key characters involved in the theme of greed and ambition are`,option:{a:"Kindo and soko",b:"Whitehead Malign and Soko",c:"Wara, Soko, Kindo",d:"King Santigi. Whitehead and Soko"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:226,question:"The traditional order in the play is represented by",option:{a:"Mrs. B",b:"Hannah",c:"Maanan",d:"Aunt"},section:"Based on J.C. De Graft’s  	Sons and Daughter. ",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:2,question:"Prince Hamlet refrains from killing King Claudius while the latter is praying because ",option:{a:"he does not want to murder a pious man ",b:"he is not yet fully convinced of his uncle’s guilt  ",c:"King Claudius might thereby gain eternal life ",d:"murder of a person paying is an unpardonable sin "},section:"question is on William Shakespeare's hamlet",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2006"},{id:456,question:"The speaker is",option:{a:"Lago",b:"Cassio",c:"Othello",d:"Desdemona"},section:`Question 15 to 20 are based on William Shakespeare's Othello. "Come, Let us go to the castle News, Friends; "Our wars are done" The Turks are drown'd. How does my old acquaintance of this isle? Honey you shall be well desired in Cyprus. I have found great love amongst them O my sweet, I prattle out of fashion and I dote in mine own comforts.`,image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:344,question:"A conscious imitation of a literary work by another with the aim of ridicule is",option:{a:"mimesis",b:"performance",c:"mockery",d:"parody"},section:"based on General Literary Principles.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:522,question:"Midsummer Night's Dream is what type of play?",option:{a:"Tragedy",b:"Farce",c:"Comedy",d:"Tragic-comedy"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:37,question:"What happened to Tess at the end of Thomas Herds Tess of the D'urbervilles?",option:{a:"She is executed for committing murder ",b:"She got married to Angel Clare ",c:"She got married to Alec D’Urbervilles ",d:"She gave birth to a baby boy."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2007"},{id:511,question:'"I am not merry, but I do beguile the thing I am, by seeming otherwise"',option:{a:"Lago",b:"Desdemona",c:"Othello",d:"Cassio"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:445,question:"Notably, one of the themes enhances the development of A Raisin in the Sun ",option:{a:"Dreams, hopes, and plans",b:"Anxiety associated with ageing",c:"Mortality",d:"Death is inevitable"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:453,question:"A good number of Kufi women secretly envy Yaremi for new",option:{a:"Marriage",b:"Liberty and freedom",c:"Loneliness",d:"Wealth"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:426,question:"In piano and drums, the poem is a reflection on the impossibility of living two different",option:{a:"Stanzas",b:"Struggles",c:"Cultures",d:"African and Ghana"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2017"},{id:82,question:"A poem written on a grand theme, in an appropriately grand style, dealing, with heroic figures is called ",option:{a:"an epigram  ",b:"an epic ",c:"a soliloquy ",d:"heroic poem"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:153,question:"The central conflict in the play is about  ",option:{a:"Lawyer Bonu’s attempt to seduce Maanan  ",b:"career choice for James Ofosu’s children  ",c:"Hannah’s lack of respect for James  ",d:"Fosuwa’s bid to force Lawyer Bonu on Maanan"},section:"Question is  based  on Joe de Graft’s Sons and Daughters.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2013"},{id:149,question:"“ I don’t see how any mother who cares for the modesty of her daughter can coolly sit down there and defend such waywardness”. “way wardness” in the except above refers to  ",option:{a:"sexual immorality  ",b:"painting  ",c:"dancing  ",d:"disobedience "},section:"Question is  based  on Joe de Graft’s Sons and Daughters.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2013"},{id:296,question:"Oxymoron is the use of two contrasting words that are",option:{a:"placed far apart",b:"different in meaning",c:"placed side by side",d:"similar in meaning."},section:"Based on General Literary Principles.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:514,question:"In literary work, verbal irony refers to a ",option:{a:"Device in which the speaker means that opposite of what he says",b:"Situation in which a character speaks or acts against the tread of events",c:"Difficult situation which defies a local or rational resolution",d:"Device in which the actor on stage means exactly what he says"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:554,question:`From the tone of Onu Kingsley Chibuike's "A government Driver on his Retirement", words such as "booze". "boomed" make it`,option:{a:"Happy",b:"Sorrowful",c:"Indifferent",d:"Joyful"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:306,question:"Life, though a vanity Yet, not purposeful In drawling<br> resignation Life’s spice is in strive<br> From the extract above, the poet suggests that",option:{a:"life is full of care",b:"there can’t be life without strive",c:"life is worthwhile without care",d:"strive makes life worth living."},section:"based on Literary Appreciation.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:279,question:"Ona has to leave her father’s house because",option:{a:"of her love for Agbadi",b:"that is the tradition",c:"her father is dead",d:"of the safety of her child."},section:"Based on Buchi Emecheta’s The Joys of Motherhood.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:341,question:"In cope’s “Sonnet VII”, poets are presented; as",option:{a:"recluses",b:"travelers",c:"sociologists",d:"searchers"},section:"based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New poetry from Africa; Soyinka W. (ed.): Poems of Black Africa: Senanu, K E and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eels.): Exam Focus: Lit¬erature in English; Eruvbetine, A. E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination guides; Nwoga, D.I (ed.): West African Verse andAdeoti G: Naked Soles.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:313,question:"James Ofosu’s desire is to see Maanan trained as",option:{a:"a choreographer",b:"an attorney",c:"an accountant",d:"a surgeon"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:523,question:"One of the following terms applies to the discussion of both tragedy and comedy",option:{a:"Climax",b:"Happy-ending",c:"Tragic hero",d:"Alliteration"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:71,question:"Farce thrives on ",option:{a:"big events ",b:"promotion ",c:"absurdity ",d:"incidents."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:544,question:'"Lord, what fools these mortals be!" In the line above, the character is',option:{a:"Expressing the behaviour of the lovers",b:"Expressing the love between two lovers",c:"Expressing the exaggerated silliness of the lovers behaviour",d:"Expressing the gift of God in their lives"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"}],n={message:e,subject:t,status:200,total:120,data:a};export{a as data,n as default,e as message,o as status,t as subject,i as total};
